From a Roman military camp called
Vindobona through its imperial heyday
that gave us all this baroque beauty,
Vienna has so much to be curious about.
Remember when you were a child and all
you ever asked was why, why, why? Well,
I never quite outgrew that whole quest
for knowledge phase. In fact, I've made
a career out of asking who, what, where,
why, and how as an arts and travel
reporter for the past 20 years.
So, if I have an insatiable [music]
curiosity about the exciting, inspiring,
beautiful world of art, architecture,
and hidden history all around [music]
us, I bet you do, too.
This isn't your typical what to do on a
vacation travel show. Oh, no. This is
your all-access pass to a deeper
understanding of the world's great art
and architecture, people and places,
history, and how did they do that?
So, come along on our educational
journey, our field trip for grown-ups
who have never quite grown up, and learn
with Curious Traveler.
>> [music]
>> Vienna is easily one of Europe's most
beautiful cities. In fact, I dare you to
try to find an ugly building around
here. It's architecture is almost
exclusively baroque. Why? Well, because
of its curious imperial history.
Willkommen in Wien.
Vienna, the architecture, the music,
[music] the coffee, and the Sachertorte.
Rivaling Paris as Europe's most
beautiful city, with centuries of royal
history, you can't [music] help but feel
a little royal yourself as you wander
this beautiful city. Vienna was once the
center of a major European empire
covering thousands of miles ruled by one
royal family for hundreds of years. And
where there are royals, you need
entertainment fit for royals. So, it was
only natural that Vienna also [music]
became a world leader of culture and
classical music.
So, here's what I'm curious about in
Vienna. Why are there so many giant
ornate public buildings all in a ring
around Vienna? Who were the Habsburgs
and Maria Theresa and Sisi?
Where did a six-year-old musical genius
perform?
When did Austria shrink to a tenth of
its original size?
Why did Francis II become Francis
[music] I?
What is this Greek goddess doing in
Vienna [music] and what do these eagles
symbolize?
And most importantly, [music] how do you
take in all of Vienna's beauty at once?
Let's begin our curious journey into
Vienna's imperial history at the heart
of the city and the heart of the empire
[music]
at the sprawling palatial complex known
as Hofburg.
The Hofburg is one of the largest royal
palaces in all of Europe with 18 wings,
19 courtyards, and 2,600
rooms. Hard to believe it all began as a
humble medieval fortress.
And you can still see remnants of its
medieval beginnings here in front of the
palace.
Like many European cities, Vienna can
trace its roots to early Celtic and
Roman settlements. I guess if the
location is good, just keep building on
top of it, right?
The original castle dates back to the
13th century and Hofburg just kept
expanding and expanding and expanding
through the 19th century.
But, apparently, even this wasn't enough
space for the royal family because there
is a summer palace, too. A sunny yellow
one called Schönbrunn.
Schönbrunn translates to beautiful
fountain and this area here actually has
some very humble beginnings. First, it
was just a farmstead and later [music]
on a simple hunting lodge, but once
Maria Theresa got a hold of it, she did
quite the makeover.
Maria Theresa was the only female ruler
of the Habsburg empire. When she wasn't
redecorating Schönbrunn, she was busy
ruling her empire for four decades
[music]
of the 18th century. During her reign,
she had several wars waged against her.
Some to contest her right to rule the
Habsburg territories. How rude. But no
problem, she dealt with it all and went
on to reform the government, improve the
military, and increase Austria's overall
wealth. She also married for love, not
power, which was rare at the time and
had 16 children. One of which was the
legendary "Let them eat cake" Marie
Antoinette.
In between all that, Maria Theresa
received Schönbrunn Palace as a wedding
[music] gift. Beats a set of steak
knives, right? And it was here in 1762
[music]
that a very important moment for Vienna
and the world happened.
>> Leopold, a very ambitious
musician, he presented his
young boy, a 6-year-old child prodigy,
Mozart. He gave a concert here at
Schönbrunn Palace in front of Maria
Theresa
and they were highly rewarded.
>> Maria Theresa was a singer herself and
because [music] of her love of music,
Mozart returned to perform in Schönbrunn
many times. We will explore his curious
life [music] in Vienna's music legacy a
bit later.
But back to that Habsburg dynasty,
[music]
about a century after Maria Theresa, one
of her descendants, Austria's legendary
Emperor Franz Joseph, was born here at
Schönbrunn Palace.
>> Emperor Franz Joseph ruled longer than
any other Austrian Emperor, 68 years in
total. Now, Schönbrunn Palace has more
than 300 rooms, but what's interesting
is that Franz Joseph chose to live most
of the time in two small rooms. This was
one of them, his bedroom, and look how
small his bed is.
>> Of his many accomplishments, Franz
Joseph's legacy includes helping to form
the Austro-Hungarian Empire.
And on a much lighter and prettier note,
he is also known for marrying the most
beloved Empress [music] in Austrian
history with a cute little nickname.
Empress Elizabeth was known as Sisi and
also known [music] for her beauty, her
charm, and her long, long hair.
There's even a popular movie series
about her. Sisi was widely loved and
adored, kind of the Princess Diana of
the 1800s. She traveled the world,
charmed heads of state, wrote poetry,
and defied convention, including
battling her meddling mother-in-law.
Sisi remains [music] an Austrian icon
today.
>> [music]
>> But before Empress Sisi, before Franz
[music] Joseph, even before the Austrian
Empire, Austria can trace its roots back
to the Middle Ages, and one of the most
powerful royal families in European
history, the Habsburgs.
>> They came from a territory which is
today's part of Switzerland.
And in the year 1278, they got control
about the territory which is the core of
today's Austria, and then they very
slowly started to build up an empire.
The Holy Roman Empire, it's a nation as
you would think of it today. So,
actually, the French philosopher
Voltaire put it quite uh
into a nutshell when he said, "The Holy
Roman Empire is neither uh holy, nor
Roman, and not an empire at all."
>> [laughter]
>> So, the Habsburgs ruled over that
non-holy, non-Roman, non-empire for
centuries.
Although the titles of those rulers
changed in the early 1800s
when Francis Napoleon the first started
causing trouble in Europe. So, a
Habsburg descendant named Francis did
something drastic to save the empire. He
ended it. And what's even more curious,
this particular Francis was born Francis
II, but died Francis
What the heck? How did Francis
become Francis cuz that doesn't normally
happen?
>> Well, yeah.
That's a typical Austrian solution. So,
he's Francis
as the Holy Roman Emperor and Francis as
the first Austrian Emperor.
>> Excellent. He just didn't want to be
number two. He wanted to be number one.
That's all it was. And it's important to
note that this Austrian Empire covered a
whole lot more than just modern-day
Austria. At its peak, it covered 10
times the size of today's country.
>> Starting from the west to today's
Austria, uh then portions, huge portions
of northern Italy,
uh then uh in the north there was uh all
of today's Czech Republic, the Silesian
parts of southern Poland, all of
Slovakia, all of Hungary, the western
portion of the Ukraine,
then uh 2/3 of today's Romania, then uh
all of Slovenia,
then Croatia, and all the northern parts
of Serbia, also Bosnia and Herzegovina.
>> Oh, is that all? So, how and why did
this huge empire split apart? Well, a
growing resentment towards imperial rule
and a little thing called World War I
happened.
>> In October 1918, the various nations,
their various ethnic or language groups
of the empire started to declare himself
independent.
>> And here's where it gets really
interesting. After those little states
were created, there almost wasn't a
little Austria left at all.
>> Austria actually was then
nicknamed the country that nobody wanted
because
at the time actually even the Austrians,
people were not so convinced about the
viability of this so much smaller
country.
>> In part because this smaller country was
incredibly vulnerable after World War I.
As the world crept towards World War II.
>> And so there was a very strong tendency
of being
fused or merged with
Germany.
>> So, after two World Wars and some
serious downsizing, Austria had a bit of
an identity crisis. So, it is no
surprise that today's Austrians and
Viennese like to identify with happier
times and the proud legacy of their
Habsburg and Imperial roots.
>> Especially as a Viennese person, you
always have this Habsburg background,
the history background. You always feel
like
still, especially when you
wander
along the Ringstrasse, you think that
Austria's still a power that matters,
which we don't. But you know, you live
on the on the backdrops of an empire.
>> What is this Ringstrasse our Viennese
friend [music] speaketh of? It is the
also grand boulevard of Vienna, a
circular [music]
one, hence the name Ringstrasse or Ring
Street. A grand project of grand
buildings, [music] parks, and gardens.
All began around 1858 under the reign of
Franz Joseph.
Much like Paris's Haussmann project,
Vienna's Ringstrasse tore down the old
city to erect the new. While the ring
follows the medieval city walls, those
actual walls were torn down. Only a few
fragments of the original wall still
remain. Like I said, throughout history,
if the location is good, just keep
building on top of the same spot. As you
play Ring around the Ringstrasse, you'll
[music] see each public building is a
temple dedicated to its function. From a
temple to music, the Vienna Opera House,
to a temple to the empire, the Hofburg
Palace. And instead of one style for all
the buildings, the Ringstrasse is a
gorgeous gallery of all different
European architectural styles, beginning
with Greek and Roman.
The Parliament buildings are perhaps the
most stunning of the Ringstrasse [music]
buildings. And you can't help but notice
it kind of looks like a Greek temple,
right? Well, that's no accident. Not
only was neoclassicism the [music]
architectural style of the time, but the
architects wanted to make the statement
that the Austro-Hungarian Empire was
just as powerful as Greece or Rome. And
standing proudly at the entrance, we
have the goddess [music] Athena, the
goddess of wisdom. And at her feet
surrounding her, we have four allegories
of the four rivers of the
Austro-Hungarian Empire.
Next around the Ringstrasse, we [music]
start to see double.
This is the beautiful Kunsthistorisches
Museum, or Fine Arts Museum. Built
between 1871 and 1891 to house the
massive art collection of the Habsburg
family. Now, the building itself is just
one of the many beautiful Baroque
buildings as part of the Ringstrasse
project. In fact, the architecture was
so popular that
they built a duplicate. That's right,
it's twin, right across the plaza. And
this building is the Natural History
Museum.
And right in the middle is our friend
Maria Theresa, still holding court high
above Vienna.
Next, for something completely [music]
different.
>> Vienna's beautiful City Hall is a little
bit different than the other buildings
along the Ringstrasse. Whereas many of
them are the Baroque style, this one is
Neo-Gothic and was modeled after many
other beautiful Gothic churches and
secular buildings found across Europe.
Now, in German City Hall translates to
Rathaus. So, if you hear someone
referring to the Rathaus, know that it's
not a commentary on politicians being
rats. Last but not least, all the way at
the top we have a beautiful statue
called the Rathausmann, which came to be
the beloved symbol of Vienna.
>> And just across from City Hall is
Vienna's Temple 2 Theater.
>> The Burgtheater was the last of the
beautiful buildings to be built here
along the Ringstrasse. We have all
around the building gorgeous decorations
of playwrights and literary figures from
throughout the centuries. At the top we
have the god Apollo with the muse of
tragedy on his right and comedy on his
left. And inside we have gorgeous
paintings by Gustav Klimt, Vienna's
favorite artist.
>> Now, for our last building, remember how
the medieval wall was torn [music] down
for the Ringstrasse? Well, there are a
few medieval buildings still standing
within the Ringstrasse. And there is one
that stands taller above the rest.
>> St. Stephen's Cathedral is a beloved
icon of Vienna. And it is believed the
version that we see today is the third
church to stand on this very spot. The
most interesting feature, of course, are
those twin spires. You can see the south
one here that extends all the way into
the heavens with the gold on top. And
then of course the matching north one on
this side at the exact same height. Oh,
wait. That one was never finished.
>> Why wasn't it ever finished? Well, there
are many legends about that, including
financial troubles, the threat of a
Turkish siege, and plain old this Gothic
style has gone out of style problems.
So, today it's fun to ponder all these
possibilities.
But more importantly, St. Stephen's
Cathedral is the symbol of Vienna. The
original church was built in the 12th
century and has a quite curious history.
It was severely damaged by fire during
World War II, but miraculously rose
again in just a few short years. Lovely
St. Stephen's Cathedral has stood tall
in the center of Vienna's inner city for
more than 700 years. [music]
Joseph Haydn was a choir boy here, and
Mozart got [music] married here.
And that unfinished North Tower was
[music] capped with a Renaissance spire
and houses the largest bell in all of
Austria. That soaring South Tower is
still the highest point in Vienna's
inner city.
But most curious of all is St. Stephen's
Cathedral's rooftop with 230,000
multi-colored glazed tiles.
On one side, there's a double-headed
eagle, and the other, two single-headed
eagles.
Why? Well, the double-headed one
represents the Habsburg empire,
symbolizing many things, including its
rule over Eastern West, rule granted by
God and the elected people, and later
the dual monarchies of Austria and
Hungary.
And what about those single-headed
eagles? This one on the left is the coat
of arms for the Republic of Austria,
with the one-headed eagle representing
Austria's sovereignty. It is often
depicted with broken chains at the
eagle's feet, symbolizing Austria's
liberation from Germany in 1945. [music]
And this one on the right is the city of
Vienna's coat of arms. The shield on the
eagle's chest with a white cross over a
red background is believed to have been
part of the seal of Vienna since the
13th century.
>> [music]
>> All that heavy history surrounded by
light and mirth here at Stephansplatz at
Christmas time.
So, let's [music] continue with some
light and mirth and beautiful classical
music, which Vienna is known around the
world for.
From the 16th to the 20th centuries,
music wasn't just [music] a light
pastime here. It was a status symbol for
the imperial family of Austria, and
Vienna became a leading European center
for music with names like Strauss,
Beethoven, and Haydn. And that fine
music legacy continues today.
Going to see a classical music concert
in Vienna in a setting like this is as
common as going to the movies. And this
luxurious setting is [music] the lovely
Palais Auersperg. Built between 1706 and
1710, it is considered Vienna's oldest
Baroque Palace, and it is a pretty darn
perfect place to listen to the world's
best classical music because not only
did Emperor Franz Joseph attend balls
here, but some of the world's best
composers performed here, including a
very special one named Wolfgang.
Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart is one of the
greatest composers in the history of
classical [music] music. The Magic
Flute, Don Giovanni, The Marriage of
Figaro, and the haunting Requiem. Mozart
is universally considered a musical
genius.
It is believed that Mozart began [music]
playing music at the age of three. And
as an adult, his genius flourished as he
was able to create music in all the
different genres of his time.
And his impact on Vienna is as grand as
his music. Even today, you can't pass a
corner in Vienna without seeing
something [music] Mozart, especially
tasty Mozartkugel chocolates. But I
digress.
But Mozart was born in Salzburg. [music]
So, why is he so linked to Vienna?
Well, the perfect person to ask that
question to is our guide at the Mozart
House, who just happens to have the same
name as Mozart's wife, Constanze.
>> What brought him here to Vienna?
>> He came here because his then boss, the
Salzburg Archbishop Colloredo, told him
to come to Vienna and to work from
Vienna for him. But then again, Mozart
was a very freedom-kind of loving person
and he was really fed up this badly paid
position. So, he had a little bit of
luck, maybe, because he had a huge fight
with the Archbishop and then he just
said, "Okay, here in Vienna, I can
become a freelance composer." And he
became one.
>> Oh, yes. From the beginning, the only
thing that rivaled Mozart's talent was
his rebellious spirit. While it was a
struggle at first, eventually Mozart
thrived in Vienna, calling it, "The land
of the piano." And some of his most
famous works were performed for the
first time here in Vienna, and written
here in Vienna, too. Some of them in
this beautiful little 17th-century
apartment.
>> This is the apartment of Mozart.
Mozart spent his last 10 years of his
life in Vienna and during the time he
moved 13 times. So, he had 14
apartments. This is the only apartment
which still exists today. All other
apartments are gone and he moved in here
on the 29th of September in 1784,
and he moved out again on the 23rd of
April in 1787. So, he lived here for
over 2 and 1/2 years, which was the
longest time he spent in an apartment.
>> But why did Mozart move so much? Did he
just have fickle tastes? Needed new
inspiration for each composition? Nope.
The reason was much more practical.
>> He never saved money. If he had money,
he just spent it all. And so, sometimes
he had to move to smaller apartments.
>> He was known for that, for the for the
money he would get, he would spend it
out on, you know, parties and and all
sort of, you know, unsavory things.
He he had a good time. Whereas maybe we
think of him as this very serious
genius. He was not a serious person at
all.
>> No, he was very very funny. He loved to
make jokes, and he loved to make up
names for for people. And
but he also worked very hard. I think
that's very fascinating about him.
>> And you can see some of his most famous
works here at the Mozart House Museum.
>> During the time he lived here, he
composed so many pieces like the opera
Le nozze di Figaro, eight piano
concertos, so sonatas, and quartets. So
many things were composed here. It's
unbelievable how he did it.
>> And today, you can stand in the very
same room where Mozart would try out his
new works for his friends.
>> But in this room also, house music
evenings would take place. So,
string people for string quartets would
come in and play the newest music of
Mozart. He would invite his friends,
guests, and they would listen to the
music. So, this all happened in this
room.
>> That's exciting. So, it's possible that
he was sitting in this room, looking out
down the same very street.
>> Sure, he did. Yeah, because the view you
have here is an authentic view, because
the houses to your left and right were
still standing um
were standing 250 years ago as well. So,
yeah, you have the same view that Mozart
had.
>> And today, you can almost hear Mozart's
music still spilling out of this window
[music] onto the streets of Vienna.
From a Holy Roman Empire that was
neither holy nor Roman nor really an
empire to a once humble Celtic [music]
settlement and Roman fort that became
the royal palace that just kept
expanding and expanding and [music]
expanding.
To a hunting lodge built on a spring
that became the sunny summer palace
where young Mozart [music] gave a
concert for Habsburg queen whose
descendant changed his name from the
second to the first and created a new
empire which paved the way for Austria's
longest [music] reigning emperor who put
a ring on Austria's most beloved empress
and another type of ring around beloved
Vienna that followed those medieval
walls and then decorated [music] it with
temples to music, art, science, culture,
government and of course the people in
all manner of shapes, styles and
symbols. And inside [music] that ring is
a proud vestige of those medieval days,
a church with a wonky tower [music]
and important symbols of Austria's
turbulent history. And just steps away
on a lovely little street, if you close
your eyes, you just might hear the music
of an Austrian-born musical genius
trying out his [music] latest
composition inside this precious
apartment above.
Vienna has so much to be curious about.
Thank you for joining us on our
educational journey and hopefully now
you're even more curious about the who,
what, where, why, when and how of
Vienna. As they say here in Austria,
"Auf Wiedersehen."
>> [music]